6. Execution Flow & Console Analysis

Console logs were used throughout the project to understand the execution flow, debug operations, and analyse program behaviour in Node.js.

1. Observing Execution Order
The application uses console.log() statements before and after major operations to track the sequence of execution. For example, the custom module demo logs the start and completion of the program execution.

Example Output:
LOG: Starting app.js...
LOG: 4 is even
LOG: 7 is odd
LOG: 10 is even
LOG: 15 is odd
LOG: 22 is even
LOG: Finished checking numbers.

2. Debugging File Operations
The File Manager utility logs each CRUD operation (Create, Read, Update, Delete) to monitor progress and identify errors during asynchronous file handling.

Logged Operations:
Creating File...
File Created
Reading File
Hello Node.js
File Updated
Hello Node.js
Learning FS Module
File Deleted
Done - file operations completed successfully

3. Analysing Server Requests
The HTTP server can be monitored using console logs when requests are received. The server handles routes such as /, /about, and /contact, returning appropriate responses.

Server Startup Log:
Server running at http://localhost:3000/

4. Tracking CLI Inputs
The calculator utility reads command-line arguments using process.argv, allowing users to pass operations and numbers from the terminal.

Example:
node calculator.js add 10 5

Output:
Result: 15

5. Understanding Synchronous vs Asynchronous Behaviour
The project demonstrates asynchronous behaviour through file operations using callback functions. Operations such as file creation, reading, updating, and deletion execute sequentially only after the previous task completes, preventing blocking of the Node.js event loop.

Observation:
• Logs appear only when each callback finishes.
• Node.js continues handling other tasks while waiting for file operations.
• This showcases non-blocking I/O, a key feature of Node.js.

Conclusion:
console.log() statements were effectively used to trace execution order, monitor CLI inputs, debug file operations, analyse server activity, and observe asynchronous execution behaviour in Node.js.

